Guide to the William Styron Papers, 1855-2019 and undated RL.01267
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Styron papers
1855-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Styron, William, 1925-2006
RL.01267
30.2 Linear Feet 24,562 items
American author and Duke University alumnus. The William Styron Papers span the years 1855-2019, with the bulk of the papers being dated between 1943 and 1996. The collection consists of correspondence; writings by Styron and other authors; printed materials (including serials containing articles by and about Styron and his work as well as newspaper and magazine clippings); audiotapes, videotapes, and photographs; legal and financial papers; speeches and addresses; interviews; scrapbooks; and other material relating to Styron's personal life and his career as a writer. Extensive personal and professional correspondence between his family, friends, and fellow authors provides insight into his education at Duke University (particularly his studies with Professor William Blackburn of the Department of English) as well as his literary career and personal life.
Access Restrictions
Restrictions apply to some parts of the William Styron Papers.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The main body of the papers of William Styron was acquired from William Styron between 1969 and 1997. Small portions of the collection were donated by others or purchased between 1970 and 2019. All of Accession 2008-0072 and parts of Accession 2008-0294 remain on deposit. Accession 2017-0068 is a gift of Linda McGrew. Accession 2019-0014 is a gift of Joel Foreman. Accession 2019-0129 is a gift of James L. W. West III. Accession 2019-0153 is a gift of Judith Ruderman.
Biographical Note
1925, June 11 Born to William Clark Styron and Pauline (Abraham) Styron, in Newport News, Va.
1942 Attended Davidson College
1943 Enlisted in Marine Corps in V-12 program Transferred to Duke University
1944-1945 Served as lieutenant in the Marine Corps
1947 Associate editor with McGraw-Hill Book Company, New York, N.Y. Received A.B. from Duke University Moved to New York City and studied writing with Hiram Haydn at the New School for Social Research
1952 Received American Academy of Arts and Letters Prix de Rome for Lie Down in Darkness (1951)
1953, May 4 Married Rose Burgunder
1960 Published the novel, Set this House on Fire
1968 Received Pulitzer Prize for The Confessions of Nat Turner (1967)
1970 Received Howells Medal of the American Academy of Arts and Letters for The Confessions of Nat Turner
1979 Publication of Sophie's Choice
1980 Received the American Book Award and nominated for the National Book Critics Circle Award, both for Sophie's Choice
1984 Received Connecticut Arts Award and Duke University's Distinguished Alumni Award Appointed a fellow of Silliman College of Yale University
1985 Received the Prix Mondial del Duca
1987 Received the Commandeur de l'Ordre des Arts et des Lettres
1988 Received Edward MacDowell Medal
1990 Publication of Darkness Visible: A Memoir of Madness, a narrative recalling the major depression Styron suffered beginning in 1985
2006 November Died at the age of 81 in Martha's Vineyard
Collection Overview
The William Styron Papers span the years 1855-2019 with the bulk of the papers being dated between 1943 and 1996. The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Writings by Styron (which includes Separate Publications, Contributions to Books and Periodicals, Speeches, Unfinished Work, and Miscellaneous Writings), Writings by Others, Printed Material, Audiovisual Material, Scrapbooks, and Miscellaneous Material. Extensive personal and professional correspondence between Styron and his family, friends, editors, and fellow authors provides insight into his education at Duke University (particularly his studies with Professor William Blackburn of the Department of English) as well as his literary career and personal life. The Writings by Styron Series includes numerous drafts, notes, manuscripts, and proofs of his novels, essays, speeches, and articles. Critical and analytical works concerning Styron's writing can be found in both the Printed Material Series and the Writings by Others Series. Interviews with Styron are to be found in both the Interviews section of the Writings by Others Series and in the Audiovisual Material Series.
Numerous American authors are represented in the collection in the Correspondence Series as well as in the Writings by Others Series. Among the major correspondents are Robert Penn Warren, Carlos Fuentes, Norman Mailer, and Reynolds Price. Letters from Eudora Welty, Truman Capote, Art Buchwald, Richard Wilbur, Kurt Vonnegut, William Kennedy, and James Dickey are also included. A separate index to some of the letters by well-known authors and celebrities accompanies the collection. The Writings by Others Series also includes limited edition copies of poems by Reynolds Price and Allen Tate.
Styron's close relationship with his family is documented in the early letters of the Correspondence Series as well as in the scrapbooks kept by his father. The latter include much juvenilia and childhood memorabilia as well as clippings documenting his early literary accomplishments. A diary kept by Styron during the year following his mother's death appears in the Writings by Styron Series: Miscellaneous Writings Subseries. The Audiovisual Material Series includes several family photographs. Videotapes in this series also provide much information about his life and work.
Among the Writings by Styron are numerous holograph notes, manuscripts written in pencil, and printed texts and typescripts with revisions. These provide detailed insight into Styron's creative process and enable the researcher to document the evolution of much of Styron's work. Research material used by Styron for some of his work, particularly The Confessions of Nat Turner, appears among the volumes in the Printed Material Series.
Styron's experience with having his work filmed for both television and the cinema is documented by screenplays of The Long March and Sophie's Choice. Several photographs of the latter production appear in the Audiovisual Material Series. A screenplay of Set This House on Fire, a first draft of a screenplay of Lie Down in Darkness, and a step outline of The Confessions of Nat Turner, none of which were produced, also appear in the Writings by Others Series
Unprocessed addition (06-105) (0.4 lin. ft) contains Styron's copy of The Confessions of Nat Turner and a binder of letters from Styron to Bertha Krantz, Robert D. Loomis, and others, 1967-1993.
Unprocessed addition (07-145) (6 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 2007) contains copies of material from Styron's memorial service, including the program, book of reminiscences, and transcript. This material is boxed in box 1 of 08-142.
Unprocessed addition (08-012) (0.8 lin. ft.; 600 items; dated 1943-2006 and undated) includes published and unpublished essays, drafts, speeches, and writings by Styron, as well as copies of letters to his father (1943-1952) and correspondence from his wife, Rose, from around the time of his death in 2006. Also includes a leather portfolio with drafts of his work, photographs, clippings, and a photograph album from his daughter's film, Shadrach.
Unprocessed addition (08-072) (180 items, .6 lin. ft.; dated 1990-2003 and undated) comprises mainly letters to Styron regarding his works, especially DARKNESS VISIBLE. Also includes letters regarding appearances requested or planned.
Unprocessed addition (08-142) (388 items, .8 lin. ft; dated 1966-2007 and undated) mainly comprises incoming correspondence, which occasionally contains clippings, photographs, and other incidental materials. In addition, includes original manuscripts for several short works by the author, many annotated, as well as some handwritten manuscript pages for SOPHIE'S CHOICE. There are also two dvds of Styron's memorial service. Box 1 of this material includes Acc. 07-145.
Unprocessed addition (08-294) (0.4 lin. ft.; 300 items) was acquired and donated by James West III, and includes manuscripts, essays, edited drafts, and speeches by Styron. Each manuscript includes a cover page by West describing the condition of the materials. This material is boxed with Acc. 08/012.
Addition (11-142) (0.6 lin. ft.; 500 items) was donated by Styron's editor, Robert Loomis. It includes drafts and clippings, as well as photographs used in Styron publications.
Additions (12-017 and 12-131) (1.2 lin. ft.; 500 items) includes various writings and research.
Addition (13-017) contains original blocks used to create advertisements for William Styron's novel The Confessions of Nat Turner.
Addition (15-030) contains correspondence with Thomas P. Peyton and Peyton's family, 1944-2002.
Addition (16-025) comprises 27 items, mainly letters and notes from Styron to Carl Mahakian. There is also an autographed photograph, and three letters to Mahakian from Jim West, who requests help with his biography of Styron. In addition, there is an invitation to Mahakian to attend Styron's private memorial service and several published obituaries, along with a Spanish translation of Darkness Visible and a Book-of-the-Month Club flyer for The Confessions of Nat Turner. Material is dated 1969-2007.
Addition (19-0014) contains 35mm documentary slides donated by Joel Foreman.
American literature -- 20th century; Duke University. Dept. of English -- History; Authors, American -- 20th century; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Styron, William, 1925-2006; Warren, Robert Penn, 1905-; Styron, William, 1925-2006 -- Biography; Blackburn, William, 1899-1972; Fuentes, Carlos; Mailer, Norman
- Correspondence Series, 1914-1997 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  The correspondence series is arranged chronologically and consists mostly of letters addressed to William Styron, but includes some written by him. Correspondents include family members, friends, teachers, publishers, and admirers of his work as well as other authors. A bound volume of letters to and from Donald Harrington is housed in box C 14 at the end of the chronologically arranged letters. Box C-15 contains restricted correspondence.
  - 1914-1953, 16 folders (Box C 1)
  - 1954-1963, 10 folders (Box C 2)
  - 1964-1967, 6 folders (Box C 3)
  - 1968-1971, 6 folders (Box C 4)
  - 1972-1977, 6 folders (Box C 5)
  - 1978-1979,Aug., 5 folders (Box C 6)
  - 1979, Sept.-1980, July, 5 folders (Box C 7)
  - 1980, Aug.-1981, June, 5 folders (Box C 8)
  - 1981, July-1983, 6 folders (Box C 9)
  - 1984-1987, 8 folders (Box C 10)
  - 1988-1989, 6 folders (Box C 11)
  - 1990, 5 folders (Box C 12)
  - 1991-1995, 9 folders (Box C 13)
  - 1996-1997, undated, 7 folders (Box C 14)
  - Correspondence with Donald Harrington (bound), 1960-1986, 1 folder (Box C 14)
  - Correspondence with Judith Ruderman, 1980-1987 (Box C 14)
    Scope and Contents
    Gift of Judith Ruderman
  - Restricted Correspondence (Box C 15)
- Writings by Styron Series, 1941-1997 and undated
  Literary works by Styron are arranged in the following subseries: Separate Publications, Contributions to Books and Periodicals, Speeches, Unfinished Work, and Miscellaneous Writings.
  - Separate Publications Subseries, 1951-1993.
    Drafts, typescripts, proofs, editions, and fragments of Styron's published monographic works, including some with Styron's revisions. Arranged chronologically by date of publication.
    - Lie Down in Darkness,1951, 1979 (Box WS 1)
      - Versions of beginning chapters, 1 folder (Box WS 1)
      - Advance galleys,1951, 1 folder (Box WS 1)
      - Page proof,1979, 3 folders (Box WS 1)
    - Set This House on Fire,1960 (Box WS 2)
      - Spiral bound galleys, 1 folder (Box WS 2)
    - The Confessions of Nat Turner, 1967
      - Research file, 1 folder (Box WS 2)
      - Advance galleys, 1 folder (Box WS 2)
      - Japanese edition, 1 volume (Box WS 3)
    - The Long March,1968
      - Carbon typescript, 1 folder (Box WS 3)
      - Screenplay, 1 folder (Box WS 3)
    - In the Clap Shack,1972
      - Fragments, 1 folder (Box WS 3)
      - Holograph, 1 folder (Box WS 3)
      - Manuscript, 1 folder (Box WS 3)
      - Manuscript with holographic revisions, 1 folder (Box WS 3)
      - Manuscript, 1 folder (Box WS 3)
    - Dead: A Love Story, 1976 (Box WS 4)
      - Manuscript, 1 folder (Box WS 4)
      - Typescript of screenplay, 1 folder (Box WS 4)
    - Message of Auschwitz, 1979,printer's proof, 1 folder (Box WS 5)
    - Sophie's Choice, 1979
      - Original holograph, 6 folders (Box WS 5)
      - Rejected manuscript pages, 1 folder (Box WS 5)
      - Setting copy, 6 folders (Box WS 6)
      - Master set, 1st pass, 3 folders (Box WS 7)
      - Master set, 2nd pass, 3 folders (Box WS 7)
      - Page proof, 2 folders (Box WS 8)
      - Galley, 3 folders (Box WS 8)
      - Miscellaneous holograph fragments, 1 folder (Box WS 8)
      - Author's corrected galleys (1 bosed item) (Box WS 9)
    - This Quiet Dust, 1982 (Box WS 10)
      - Corrections, 1 folder (Box WS 10)
      - Setting copy, 2 folders (Box WS 10)
      - Proof, 2 folders (Box WS 10)
      - Galley proof, 2 folders (Box WS 11)
      - Introduction and 4 new holograph essays, 1 folder (Box WS 11)
    - Darkness Visible, 1990 (Box WS 12)
      - Galleys for Vanity Fair version, 1 folder (Box WS 12)
      - Book jackets, 1 folder (Box WS 12)
      - Early holograph fragments, 1 folder (Box WS 12)
      - Incomplete holograph, 1 folder (Box WS 12)
      - Final manuscript, 1 folder (Box WS 12)
      - Page proof, 2 folders (Box WS 12)
      - Proof, 1 folder (Box WS 12)
      - Author's galleys, 1 folder (Box WS 12)
      - Typescript with revisions, 1 folder (Box WS 12)
    - A Tidewater Morning, 1994 (Box WS 13)
      - Front material, book jackets, 1 folder (Box WS 13)
      - A Tidewater Morning, galley,1987, 1 folder (Box WS 13)
      - "Shadrach," manuscript and typescript, n.d (1 folder) (Box WS 13)
      - Setting manuscript, 1 folder (Box WS 13)
      - Die copy, 1 folder (Box WS 13)
      - Master set, 1st pass, 1 folder (Box WS 13)
      - Master set, 2nd pass, 1 folder (Box WS 13)
      - Proof, 1 folder (Box WS 13)
      - Page proof, 1 folder (Box WS 13)
  - Contributions to Books and Periodicals Subseries, 1944-1996 and undated
    Typescripts, manuscripts, and photocopies of Styron's contributions to books and periodicals are divided into the following sections: Short Stories, Essays and Articles, and Introductions and Contributions to the Works of Others. Within each section, the material is arranged chronologically by date of publication.
    - Short Stories (Box WS 14)
      - 1944, Jan., The Archive - "Where the Spirit Is", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1944, Mar., The Archive - "The Long Dark Road", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1944, Sept., The Archive - "Sun on the River", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1944, Dec., The Archive - "A Story About Christmas", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1945, Feb., The Archive - "Autumn,", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1946, May, The Archive - "This is My Daughter", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1946, Oct., The Archive - "The Ducks" (1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1965, April, Harper's Magazine - "This Quiet Dust", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1978, Mar. 14, Esquire - "My Life as a Publisher", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1985, May 7, Esquire - "Love Day", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1995, Sept. 18, New Yorker - "A Victim of the Great Pox", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1996, April, Paris Review - "Transcontinental with Tex", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
    - Essays and Articles
      - 1946, Sept., The Archive - Review of An Almanac for Moderns by Daniel C. Peattie, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1946, Oct., The Archive - Essay on Dr. Newman Ivy White (1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1946, Dec., The Archive - Essay on Dr. Joseph Banks Rhine, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1961, in The Artists' and Writers' Cookbook - "Southern Fried Chicken", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1965, June, Harper's Magazine - Letter to Harper's Magazine, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1969, Spring, in The Southern Literary Journal - "The Use of History in Fiction", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1972, Summer, American Scholar - Review of The Aonheiter Affair, by Neil Sheehan, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1972, June, New York Times Book Review - Review of Lt. Calley, by John Sack and The Court-Martial of Lt Calley, by Richard Hammer, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1972, Mar., The Washington Monthly - Review of 365 Days, by Ronald J. Glasser, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1973, May6, New York Times Book Review - Review of A Second Flowering, by M. Cowley, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1974, June, New York Times - Op-ed page, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1976, Dec. 19, Washington Post - "Potomac", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1981, NY Review of Books - Review of The Civil War, by Mary Chestnut, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1982, Jan., The Hartford Courant - Account of writing Lie Down in Darkness, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1983, May, Le Figaro - Essay on influence of cinema on his writing (Box WS 14)
      - 1983, Dec., Esquire - "The Harbor: Edgartown, MA, Aug.1963" (Box WS 14)
      - 1984, Fall, Architectural Digest - Essay on Thomas Wolfe's house, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1985, Aug., Esquire - "Love Day,", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1987, May 10,New York Times - "Death Row", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1987, June, Esquire - Essay on Virginia Foster Durr, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - ca. 1987, Observer and New York Times Book Review Essay on James Baldwin, 2 folders (Box WS 14)
      - 1988, Dec. 21, New York Times - Op-ed piece on Primo Levi, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1989, Aug., Vanity Fair - Essay on Irwin Shaw, 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1989, Dec., Vanity Fair - "From the Abyss: Reflections of My Mind's Disorder", 2 folders (Box WS 14)
      - 1991, April4, Time - "A Father's Prophecy", 1 folder (Box WS 14)
      - 1991, June 16, New York Times Book Review - Review of Fortunate Son, by Lewis B. Puller, Jr., 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1991, Oct., Vineyard Gazette - Review of Deadline, by James Reston, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1992, American Heritage, Oct. - "Nat Turner Revisited" (Box WS 15)
      - 1992, Time - Essay on the family, 2 folders (Box WS 15)
      - 1993, Jan.4, Newsweek - Article on Hiroshima and Auschwitz, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1993, Sept., Newsweek - Essay on depression, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1993, The Nation [v. 256, n. 1] - "Prozac Days, Halcion Nights", 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1994, Summer, Audubon Magazine - Response to proposed Disney theme park in Virginia, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1994, Dec., American Heritage - Comment, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1995, Apr. 23, New York Times - Letter (Box WS 15)
      - 1995, June, The New Yorker - Essay on Mark Twain, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1995, Aug., The New Yorker - Essay on Lolita, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1995, Oct.8, New York Times Book Review - "A Childhood Transgression", 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1996, Jan., Le Monde - Essay on the death of Mitterand (Box WS 15)
      - 1996, Cigar Aficionado - Essay on JFK and cigars, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1996, Egoiste - Essay on Terazosin, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated, High Fidelity - Review of JFK: As We Remember Him, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated, New York Times Book Review - Review of The Joint, by James Blake, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated, New York Times Book Review - Review of Reminiscences, by Douglas MacArthur, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated, London Observer - Essay on James Baldwin, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
    - Introductions and Contributions to Works of Others
      - 1975, May - Preface for a bibliography by James L.W. West III, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1982, Jan.- Introduction for the Franklin Mint edition of The Confessions of Nat Turner, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1982, Feb.- Introduction for the French edition of Whistler, by James Jones, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1982, April- Introduction for The Wheat and the Chaff, by Francois Mitterand, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1983, June- Introduction for The Cunning of History, by Richard Rubenstein, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1988 - Introduction for US-Soviet collaborative prose and poetry collection, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1988, Sept.- Afterward to Bernard Faber article, published in Esquire, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1988 - Preface for The View from Space, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1989 - Introduction for Letters of James Jones, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1990 - Introduction to Doing Justice, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1993 - Introduction for The Face of Mercy, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1995 - Introduction to Convicting the Innocent, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - 1996 - Introduction for Dog Eat Dog, by Edward Bunkin, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated - Introduction for A Death in Canaan, by Joan Barthel, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated - Introduction for Paris Review volume of interviews, 9th series, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated - Introduction for Inheritance of Night, by William Styron, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated - Introduction for The Human Experience, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated - Introduction for Writers at Work, Vol. 9, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated - Introduction for No Beast So Fierce, by Edward Bunker, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated - Introduction for Fathers and Daughters, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated - Introduction for portfolio of etchings by Harold Altman, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated - Essay for Betsy Locke's book on Duke alumni, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
      - Undated - "On Hellman, for book by Roddy McDowell, 1 folder (Box WS 15)
  - Speeches Subseries, 1942-1996 and undated
    Transcripts of speeches written and mostly presented by Styron at commencements, memorial services, conferences, and award ceremonies, and upon other occasions. Arranged chronologically by date of presentation.
    - 1942 - Commencement address at Christchurch School, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1973, May- Commencement address at Christopher Newport College, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1975, April 4 - "Admiral Robert Penn Warren and the Snows of Winter," New York City Lotus Club, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1975, April 10- Tribute to Robert Penn Warren, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1975, May- Speech on Howells Medal, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1975 - Commencement address at Christchurch School, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1980, May- "Almost A Rhodes Scholar: A Personal Reminiscence", 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1980 - Commencement address at Hampden-Sydney College, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1981, May 11- Commencement address at Duke University, 2 folders (Box WS 16)
    - 1981, July - Account of the inaugural of Francois Mitterrand, Boston Globe (Box WS 16)
    - 1982, April 26- "Virginian of the Year" acceptance speech, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1982, April 27- Address at Carnegie Hall, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1983, January- Speech at NY Film Critics Award ceremony, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1983, May 28- Commencement address at Taft School, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1983 - "Mr. Jefferson and Our Times," Convocation address at University of Virginia, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1984, Sept. 25- Truman Capote memorial, 1 folder (Box WS 16)
    - 1984, Oct. 27- Connecticut Arts Award acceptance speech, 1 folder (Box WS 16)